Juan Kuntz Nussio

Profile

Versatile Research Scientist with

- o a knack for working across disciplines and a **broad background** in mathematics, computer science, and engineering;
- o ample experience in computational statistics, machine learning, Monte Carlo, optimization, & control theory;
- o proficiency in **Python** and keen interest in software development;
- o and ten years of experience in academic research.

Scientific Skills

Computational statistics: Frequentist inference, Bayesian inference, (marginal) maximum likelihood/a posterior estimation, bias-variance trade-offs, statistical efficiency, variational inference, expectation-maximization, empirical Bayes, hidden Markov models, filtering/smoothing, hierarchical models, and gradient-flow methods (e.g. SVGD).

Machine learning: Un/self-/supervised learning, neural networks, autoencoders, probabilistic and energy-based models (VAEs, GANs, and diffusion models, etc.), contrastive and score-matching training techniques, and a working knowledge of reinforcement learning (bandits, dynamic programming, TD learning, actor-critic methods, etc.).

Monte Carlo: Rejection sampling, importance sampling, Markov chain Monte Carlo, annealed importance sampling, sequential Monte Carlo, pseudo-marginal methods, mutilevel Monte Carlo, likelihood-free methods, debiasing techniques, and variance reduction techniques (control variates, antithetic variates, Rao-Blackwellization, etc.).

Optimization: Standard convex programs (LPs, SDPs, etc.), primal-dual formulations, first-order methods, stochastic optimization, proximal algorithms, higher-order methods, algorithms for constrained optimization (IPMs, ADMM, etc.), and derivative-free methods (coordinate descent, Bayesian optimization, simulated annealing, genetic algorithms, etc.).

Control theory: Stability and Lyapunov theory, linear systems theory, linearization techniques, optimal control, robust control, system identification techniques, and model predictive control.

Broader mathematics: Numerical analysis, probability theory, optimal transport, differential geometry, dynamical systems, stochastic processes, Markov processes, and measure theory.

Languages

Bilingual in Spanish and English, proficient in French.

Languages 'Languages'

Publications

13 academic publications including **9 first-author journal articles** and **a book**; see my website for a searchable list with subject tags. **h-index** of **8** and **151 total citations**, as indicated by Google Scholar in Oct. 2022. Latest publications:

- o J. Kuntz, J. N. Lim and A. M. Johansen. "Scalable particle-based alternatives to EM". AISTATS (under review, 2022).
- **J. Kuntz**, F. R. Crucinio, and A. M. Johansen. "Product-form estimators: exploiting independence to scale up Monte Carlo". *Statistics and Computing* 32.12 (2022).

Work Experience

Postdoctoral Research Fellow. Department of Statistics, University of Warwick, UK.	Apr 2020 – today
Postdoctoral Research Associate. Department of Bioengineering, Imperial College London, UK.	Nov 2017 – Jun 2019
Research Assistant. Department of Bioengineering, Imperial College London, UK.	Mar 2017 – Aug 2017
Research Assistant. Department of Chemistry, Imperial College London, UK.	Oct 2016 – Feb 2017
Research Assistant. Department of Mathematics, Imperial College London, UK.	Jan 2015 – Jun 2015

Education

Ph.D. in Bioengineering and Mathematics.

Oct 2012 - Oct 2017

Imperial College London, UK., Funded by a BBSRC Studentship.

Thesis: "Deterministic approximation schemes with computable errors for the distributions of Markov chains".

M.Eng. in Biomedical Engineering.

Oct 2008 – Jul 2012

Imperial College London, UK., Graduated with First-Class Honours (ranked second in year group).

• Integrated Masters degree (Bachelors + Masters) with a one-year specialization in Control Engineering.